Guide to the Mick Moloney Irish-American Music and Popular Culture Collection, Part II: Field Recordings AIA.031.002
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Mick Moloney Irish-American Music and Popular Culture Collection, Part II: Field Recordings
Bulk, 1974-1997
1956–2001 (bulk 1974-1997)
AIA.031.002
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
38.0 linear feet (38 boxes)
Part II of the Mick Moloney Irish-American Music and Popular Culture Collection at the Tamiment Library, New York University consists of field recordings made and collected by Dr. Moloney in the course of his career as folklorist, producer, musician and academic. The recordings include interviews and private performances, commercial recording sessions, rehearsals, demos, concert performances, informal group sessions, ceilis, competitions, lectures and broadcasts. The majority of the original tapes are ¼″ reel-to-reels and audio cassettes but also include some 8, 16 and 24-track master reels. A percentage of the recordings have been digitized and exist on reference CDs to be used by researchers. NOTE: This collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mick Moloney Irish American Music and Popular Culture Collection, Part I: Commercial Recordings (AIA 031.1)
Mick Moloney Irish American Music and Popular Culture Collection, Part III: Mick Moloney Papers (AIA 031.3)
Mick Moloney Irish American Music and Popular Culture Collection, Part IV: Irish Americana (AIA 031.4)
Dorothy Hayden Cudahy Irish Memories Collection (AIA 001)
Susan McKeown Papers (AIA 032)
Arrangement
The field recordings are arranged in two series:
Series I: Digitized Tapes, 1965-1997
Series II: Non-digitized Tapes, 1956-2001
Within each of these series, recordings made in a private context are arranged alphabetically by artist, and recordings made in a public context are arranged chronologically.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Mick Moloney Irish-American Music and Popular Culture Collection in the Archives of Irish America at the Tamiment Library, New York University constitutes an aurally and visually rich resource for scholars and students of the Irish-American experience. Field recordings made or collected by Mick Moloney with artists and participants in the Irish traditional music world in the United States and abroad make up Part II of this collection. The field recordings were made in his capacity as a producer of albums of Irish traditional music; as a folklorist; and as artistic director for International House Philadelphia and for the musical ensemble, The Green Fields of America.
Dr. Mick Moloney (b. 1944, Limerick, Ireland) is Global Distinguished Professor of Music and Irish Studies at New York University. He immigrated to the United States in 1973 and was based in Philadelphia until moving to New York City in 2006. A musician and folklorist, he has recorded and produced over forty albums of traditional music and acted as advisor for scores of festivals and concerts, as well as being artistic director for the musical ensemble, The Green Fields of America. In 1999 Mick Moloney was awarded the National Heritage Award of the National Endowment for the Arts, the highest official honor a traditional artist can receive in the United States. He is the author of the book and CD Far from the Shamrock Shore (2002), as well as numerous essays on Irish music and musical culture, and is co-editor of Close to the Floor: Irish Dance from the Boreen to Broadway (2009). He holds a Ph.D. in folklore and folklife from the University of Pennsylvania.
For further biographical information, see:
Steve Winnick, “From Limerick Rake to Solid Man: The Musical Life of Mick Moloney,” Dirty Linen, No. 48 (October/November 1993)
1999 NEA National Heritage Fellowships online at http://www.nea.gov/honors/heritage/fellows/fellow.php?id=1999_11
Mick Moloney, Musician and Folklorist, at http://www.mickmoloney.com
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
CDs of the recordings that have been digitized are available for listening on-site at the Tamiment Library or at the Avery Fisher Center for Music and Media at NYU. Researchers interested in undigitized recordings may request that a reference copy be made free of charge, which they may then listen to on-site.
In some cases there may be some preservation work required before digitization can be performed, as indicated in the container list by the phrases, "Needs some preservation work before digitization" or "Needs significant preservation work before digitization." Researchers may be responsible for a percentage of the cost of this preservation work.
NOTE: This collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
New York University’s Division of Libraries, in conjunction with Glucksman Ireland House at New York University, purchased the Mick Moloney Collection for the Archives of Irish America in 2006. Until the Collection was transferred to New York University, under the supervision of Dr. Michael Nash, Head of the Tamiment Library, the materials were stored in Dr. Moloney’s house in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
Under two Archiving and Preservation Grant from the Grammy Foundation in 2007 and 2008, New York University’s Division of Libraries has digitally preserved approximately a quarter of the 1237 tapes (around 252 hours), while 891 tapes (around 715 hours) exist only in their original format.
Scope and Content Note
The Moloney field recordings document the Irish-American traditional music scene between 1956 and 2001 (bulk dates 1974 to 1997). The collection features 115 formal and informal interviews and hundreds of musical performances from instrumental virtuosi, including a significant number of women musicians, ranging from live concert performances to recording and informal sessions. In addition the collection uniquely documents Mick Moloney’s own career. Part II consists primarily of ¼″ reel-to-reels and audio cassettes but also includes some 8, 16 and 24-track master reels. Approximately a quarter of the recordings have been digitized and exist on reference CDs to be used by researchers.
Series I: Digitized Tapes, 1965-1997 consists of recordings that have been digitized. They are available to researchers on reference CDs, which must be listened to in the Tamiment reading room or at the Avery Fisher Center for Music and Media. In most cases the reference CD folders include paper summaries and inventories of the tape's contents.
Series II: Non-digitized Tapes, 1956-2001 consists of recordings that have not been digitized and exist only in their original format. Reference CDs for these tapes will be made on request and must also be listened to on-site.
No copies of anything in either series will be given to researchers unless they themselves contact and receive permission from the performers or interviewees on the tapes.
Within both series the tapes have been grouped according to the recording situation in which they were made: private performances (without an audience) and public performances. Some of the highlights of these two categories are detailed below.
Private Performances include interviews, recording sessions, rehearsals and demos with both recording veterans and musicians just beginning their careers. Several of the artists recorded (Kevin Burke, Liz Carroll, Jack Coen, Donny Golden, Michael Flatley, Joe Heaney, Mick Moloney, Martin Mulvihill, Joe Shannon) were subsequently awarded National Heritage Fellowships from the National Endowment for the Arts.
During his earliest years in the United States (1976-1980) Mick Moloney sought out musicians in the Boston, Chicago, Detroit, New York and Philadelphia areas. Among the first was Co. Cavan fiddler Ed Reavy (1897-1988), whose compositions pervade the twentieth-century Irish traditional music repertoire, recorded in Philadelphia in 1974, 1977 and 1979. Flute player Eddie Cahill (b. 1929) was recorded on nine separate occasions in 1977 and 1978. Then one of the leading proponents of the Sligo-style of playing that had come to dominate Irish traditional music due to the influence of 78rpm recordings, Cahill (in a June 5, 1977 interview) describes his stylistic debt to John McKenna whose records he heard at home in Annagh Beg, Co. Sligo before immigrating to Philadelphia in 1950. Likewise, Moloney sought out Al Purcell, a student of the great Leo Rowsome in Dublin. In 1978 Purcell was a wooden model maker for General Motors in Detroit, who not only played and taught the uilleann pipes but repaired and made reeds for them as well. Liz Carroll was first recorded by Moloney in 1976, just after winning the All-Ireland Senior Championship on the fiddle at age eighteen. A native of Chicago and a composer often compared with Ed Reavy, Carroll learned from older musicians like fiddler Johnny McGreevy. McGreevy (b. 1919), uilleann piper Joe Shannon (b. 1919) and pianist Eleanor Kane Neary (b. 1915) are among the Chicago musicians Dr. Moloney frequently recorded. Neary, who played at the 1934 World’s Fair, made only one 78rpm solo recording that was commercially released; the Moloney Collection has over eight hours of her performances.
Others notable players recorded by Mick Moloney in private settings include fiddlers Paddy Cronin, Andy McGann, Paddy Reynolds and Eugene O’Donnell; flute players Mike Rafferty, Noel Rice, and Richard Hughes; uilleann pipers Tim Britton, Bill Ochs, Jerry O'Sullivan and Joe McKenna; Paddy O’Brien and Gene Kelly, accordion; concertina player Fr. Charlie Coen; and sean nós singer Paddy Tunney. Mary Cooley from Chicago was among the first women artists recorded by Mick Moloney; he documented her talent in 1978 shortly after she had won the 1977 All-Ireland Championship in Ladies Irish Singing.
Mick Moloney also made contact with American musicians who were developing interests in Irish traditional music, such as the folklorist I. Sheldon Posen and guitarist Duck Baker. Posen made a 1977 recording that was eventually included on an album Moloney produced in 1991 ( The Music of Ed Reavy), while Baker recorded tunes that later appeared on his 1979 album Irish Reels, Jigs, Hornpipes and Airs.
Many other recording sessions including out-takes, alternate cuts, rough mixes and unreleased albums are to be found in this part of the collection. These include projects by Maureen and John Fitzpatrick, Sean McGlynn and Mike Flynn, Gus Collins, Joe Ryan and Eddie Clarke, James Keane and Jack and Fr. Charlie Coen.
Among the interviews that are of historic importance, are composer/entertainer Shay Healy (b. 1943) who was working in Nashville in 1974; Dennis Clark (1927–1993), historian of the Irish in America, recorded in 1978 at the height of the “roots” phenomena; sean nós singer Joe Heaney (1919–1984) interviewed in 1981 and 1982 while living in Bay Ridge, Brooklyn; the 1977 reflections of banjo player Mike Flanagan (1898–1990) of the Flanagan Brothers, popular recording artists of the 1920s and early 1930s; Mickey Carton, Mary Carton, and Ruthie Morrissey reminiscing in 1982 about their career on the Rockaway cabaret circuit; Eileen McNulty, last surviving member of the Famous McNulty Family; Arthur Godfrey Show regular Carmel Quinn; Clare fiddler Junior Crehan while on tour of the United States in 1976; “Cuz” Teehan, the Chicago accordion and concertina player, speaking in 1976 with Mick Moloney and Irish broadcaster and music collector Ciarán MacMathúna; the three founders of the Irish Musicians Association interviewed in 1977 in the cities where they each set up branches: Ed Reavy (Philadelphia), Louis Quinn (New York), and Frank Thornton (Chicago); three radio hosts, Tommy Caulfield and Will Regan (both Philadelphia) and Dorothy Hayden Cudahy (New York City); a 1977 interview with Pat Roche, founder of the Harp and Shamrock School of Traditional Dance in Chicago; a March 1990 interview with Irish folk singer Paddy Clancy (1922-1998) when he was in Willow Grove, PA. and a 1991 interview with Tommy Makem (1932-2007) in San Francisco.
Some of the interviews were recorded as source material for liner notes written by Mick Moloney, particularly for Jack and Charlie Coen’s 1977 album The Branch Line (Topic), The Martin Mulvihill School - Irish Music: The Living Tradition (Green Linnet, 1977), Johnny Cronin and Joe Burke (Shanachie, 1977), and The Corner House by the Irish Tradition (Green Linnet, 1978).
There are a few exceptions to the Irish-American focus of these field recordings such as a private performance by the Co. Clare fiddler Bobby Casey (1926-2000), recorded in London in 1973, and private performances by famed Ballinakill flute player, Eddie Moloney. Some of these recordings were probably not recorded by Moloney but ended up in his possession and are included here. Other examples of tapes inherited by Moloney include early compilation tapes made by the composer Ed Reavy (1897–1988) and accordionist, Charlie Mulvihill (1917-1975). These include several examples of private performances and home-made 78rpm recordings transferred to tape, which were then circulated among musicians in the United States during the 1950s and 1960s.
Public Performances include concert performances, sessions, ceilis, competitions, lectures and broadcasts.
Informal music sessions from New York, Washington DC, Cleveland, Chicago, Milwaukee, and San Francisco and many in Mick Moloney’s homes in Philadelphia in the 1970s are included in this series. The earliest is a 1965 home recording from the Bronx with traditional musicians Ed Reavy, Johnny Cronin, Mike Preston, Paddy Murphy, Denis Murphy, John McMahon and J. McAulliffe. There are two rare pub session recordings from early 1976: an evening at the Bunratty in the Bronx, NY with Paddy Reynolds, Andy McGann, Johnny Cronin (fiddles), Patty Moriarty (accordion) and Mick Moloney (guitar, banjo, vocals); and one with the John Glynn Branch of the Irish Musicians Association at the Breffni Inn in Queens, New York. Glynn, an accordion player, had an influential school of music in Brooklyn at the time.
Mick Moloney recorded the tradition as it was being taught as well as played. Tapes of Martin Mulvihill’s School of Irish Music in the Bronx, Father Charlie Coen’s Children’s Choir on Staten Island, and the 1978 Comhaltas Ceoltóirí Éireann Fleadh Cheoil competition at Manhattan College in the Bronx (a.k.a. New York Fleadh) are included. He seized the opportunity to document young musicians who later blossomed into traditional Irish music stars, including twelve-year-old fiddler Eileen Ivers and fifteen-year-old Seamus Egan (mandolin, flute, whistle, uilleann pipes, banjo). Ivers (now a nine time All-Ireland fiddle champion) can be heard playing in 1977 with a youth ceili band for the Green Linnet album Irish Music, the Living Tradition. Egan was recorded in 1984 playing banjo at a Philadelphia session with Liz Carroll, Jimmy Keane and Mick Moloney, as well as in two pub sessions that same summer in Miltown Malbay, Co. Clare. Moloney later showcased both Ivers and Egan in his touring ensemble, Mick Moloney and Friends, and this part of the collection features many examples of their playing in the 1990s. A twenty-year old Michael Flatley was recorded playing the flute in Chicago in 1978; the following year he performed with Mick Moloney as part of the pioneering touring ensemble, The Green Fields of America.
Concert performances include Moloney's own ensemble The Green Fields of America; the first American concerts by the Irish traditional supergroups the Chieftains (1974), De Danann (1978) and Clannad (1979); and performances at such legendary venues as the Eagle Tavern in New York City, the Cherry Tree in Philadelphia, and Godfrey Daniels in Bethlehem, PA. In 1983 Moloney helped organize the ensemble Cherish the Ladies, represented here by recordings with sean nós singers Treasa Ui Cearuil and Bridget Fitzgerald as well as by a 1988 performance in Woodside, New York during the height of undocumented immigration from Ireland. That concert featured the young Irish American musician Joanie Madden (1983 All-Ireland gold medalist on tin whistle and flute). Of particular interest is the three-hour February 1990 benefit concert for Joe Doherty, an Irish political prisoner held by American authorities while fighting extradition to the United Kingdom, which was the occasion for a historic gathering of a veritable “who’s who” of Irish traditional musicians at Symphony Space in New York City. Only excerpts from this concert were included on the 1991 Green Linnet record The Rights of Man.
Two foreign tours funded by the United States Information Agency are represented here by a September 1983 concert performance at the Hotel Ivoire, Abidjan, Cote d’Ivoire, in Africa with Mick Moloney (banjo, guitar), Liz Carroll (fiddle), Donny and Eileen Golden (dancing); and by a May 1985 concert performance at the ruins of the Grand Hotel (Casa Grande) in Managua, Nicaragua with Susie Goff and the Green Grass Cloggers, Mick Moloney (mandolin) and Robbie O’Connell (guitar, vocals). The former was part of the Festival of Traditional American Dance; the latter part of the Festival of Mountain Music and Dance.
In 1975 Mick Moloney also began to document outdoor festivals in the United States at which Irish traditional music was featured, beginning with a concert in Philadelphia’s Lenape Park that became the genesis for the Philadelphia Ceili Group Festival. The collection documents several years of this festival as well as the 1976 Smithsonian Folklife Festival, whose Irish segment was curated by Moloney. He travelled to Leeds in New York’s Catskill mountains where, in 1978, he recorded Billy McComiskey (accordion), Andy McGann (fiddle), Maureen Doherty (flute) and the Clancy Brothers with Tommy Makem, among others. By the 1980s Moloney was a regular at the Cuyahoga Valley National Recreation Area in Cleveland, OH; at the Augusta Heritage Center, in Elkins, WV and at Milwaukee Irish Fest in Milwaukee, WI. All of these festivals are well documented here.
In addition to numerous academic lectures presented by Moloney in Ireland and America, this part of the collection features many interesting Moloney-related radio broadcasts. Of particular historic interest is Across the Western Ocean: The Story of Irish Traditional Music in America, a National Public Radio series written, hosted and produced by Mick Moloney in 1978. Its thirteen episodes are a musical snapshot of Irish America in the wake of the twelve part Roots phenomenon, aired just one year earlier.
Among items in this series inherited by Mick Moloney are tapes uilleann piper and radio host Thomas Standeven made of the John Vesey Trio in 1974. Vesey (1924-1995), one of Philadelphia’s finest fiddlers in the Sligo tradition, only made private recordings between 1954 and 1974. Inherited as well is a recording made by Irish broadcaster Ciarán MacMathúna for his Sunday morning radio program Mo Cheol Thú on Radio Telefis Éireann (RTE), which captured a ceili led by Larry Redican at the Commodore Barry Club/Philadelphia Irish Center in the early 1970s. Three short interviews (two in the Irish language with recent immigrants from Falcarragh, Co. Donegal) conducted by MacMathúna can be found in this series because they precede the ceili; the one in English with Nancy McCahill concerns the creation of the Philadelphia Irish Center.
A note on numbering: Each tape is numbered with an aiamm (Archives of Irish America Mick Moloney) number and a C or R suffix indicating format (cassette or reel). Once a tape has been digitized, its reference CD can be located by box and folder; original tapes and their Gold CD masters can be located by box and aiamm number.
A note on description: In cases where the tapes were too fragile to be listened to, information from the tape box has been transcribed verbatim and appears in quotes in the container list. In addition, any markings from the original tape boxes which might indicate context also appear in quotes.
NOTE: This collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Britton, Tim; Cahill, Eddie; Carroll, Liz, 1957-; Coen, Charlie, Fr., 1934-; Coen, Jack; Egan, Seamus, 1969-; Ivers, Eileen; Keane, James, 1948-; Keane, Jimmy; McComiskey, Billy; McGlynn, Sean; McGreevy, Johnny, 1919-; Moloney, Mick (Michael); Neary, Eleanor Kane, 1915-1993; O'Connell, Robbie; O'Donnell, Eugene, 1932-; Ochs, Bill; Rafferty, Mike, 1926-; Boston (Mass.); Broadcasts.; Ceili.; Chicago (Ill.); Cleveland (Ohio); Competitions.; Compilation.; Composition (Music); Concerts.; Demonstrations (presentation events).; Detroit (Mich.); Interviews.; Irish Americans |x Music.; Irish Americans |x Social life and customs.; Irish in America.; Irish Songs and music.; Irish |x Music.; Music festivals.; Music schools.; Music |x Competitions.; New York (N.Y.); Oral history.; Philadelphia (Pa.).; Practice (rehearsal).; Private performance.; Recording session.; Saint Paul (Minn.); San Francisco (Calif.); Washington (D.C.); Workshops (seminars)
- Series I: Digitized Tapes, 1965-1997
  - I:A Reference CDs of Digitized Tapes
    - Private Performances, 1970-1992, circa 1970-Jan 27, 1992
      - Baker, Duck (guitar) Recording session and interview in Philadelphia, PA. for the 1979 Kicking Mule release, Irish Reels, Jigs, Hornpipes and Airs. (Two CDs – Total length: 00:13:57) aiamm301R, Jul 23, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Brittingham, Frank (pub owner). Interview recorded in Brittingham’s Irish Pub and Restaurant, Lafayette Hill, PA. Brittingham discusses his personal history and his pub, a venue for Irish music in the Philadelphia area. (Two CDs – Total length: 01:04:17) aiamm344C, May 15, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Britton, Tim (uilleann pipes) Recording session at Mick Moloney’s home, 5321 Germantown Ave., Philadelphia, PA. for the 1979 Rounder release, Light Through the Leaves. (One CD – Length: 00:18:36) aiamm269R, Jan 29, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Britton, Tim (uilleann pipes) Recording session and interview in Philadelphia, PA. (Four CDs – Total length: 00:42:28) aiamm266R, 267R, 268R, Jan 3, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Burke, Joe “Banjo” (banjo and voice, b. 1946, Johnstown, Co. Kilkenny, d. Dec, 2003, Albany, New York) Interview at the Bunratty Pub, Bronx, NY. Burke provides biographical and musical information for the sleeve notes of his 1977 Shanachie recording with fiddler Johnny Cronin. (One CD – Length: 00:19:53) aiamm134R, Feb 18, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Byrne, Tom (flute, b. May 28, 1920, Co.Sligo) Interview in Cleveland, OH. Byrne discusses his personal and musical experiences in Ireland and Cleveland. (One CD – Length: 00:52:10) aiamm2R, Apr 27, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Byrne, Tom (flute, b. May 28, 1920, Co.Sligo), McCaffrey, Tom (fiddle, b. 1916, Co. Leitrim) and Noonan, Jimmy (flute, b. 1963, Cleveland, OH) Interview in Cleveland, OH. Byrne and McCaffrey, mainstays of the Cleveland Irish music community, and teenaged Noonan discuss: their personal and musical histories, Irish music in Cleveland. (Three CDs – Total length 01:38:20) aiamm2R, 3R, Apr 27, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Cahill, Eddie (flute, b. Annagh Beg, Co. Sligo), Vesey, John (fiddle, b. Apr 21, 1924, Ballincurry, Co. Sligo, d. 1995), Moloney, Mick (guitar, b. Nov 15, 1944, Co. Limerick) Recording session in Philadelphia. Musician, collector and scholar Moloney is a National Heritage Fellowship recipient. (One CD – Length 00:22:59) aiamm114R, Feb 6, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Cahill, Eddie (flute) Private performance of traditional music and interview recorded in Philadelphia. Sligo style flute player Cahill briefly plays then discusses: his personal and musical history, the Sligo style, Irish music in Philadelphia. (One CD – Length 00:33:10) aiamm5R, Jun 5, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)